Guide to the Enid Bagnold Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Enid Bagnold papers
1912-1971
GEN MSS 78
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1
(4 boxes)
The papers contain personal and professional correspondence and other papers, including a scrapbook, which document Bagnold's personal life and writing career.
Bagnold, Enid
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were purchased by The Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library in April 1982 from the George S. MacManus Company with income from the Herman W. Liebert Book Fund.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 4: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
ENID BAGNOLD, LADY JONES (1889-1981)
Enid Bagnold, a twentieth-century British author, is best known for her novel National Velvet (1935) and her play "The Chalk Garden" (1955). Born in Rochester, England she spent much of her early life abroad. As a child Bagnold lived in Jamaica where her father was stationed with the Royal Engineers. She was educated in Germany and France.
During World War I, Bagnold served in an English hospital and drove an ambulance for the French army. Drawing on these experiences, she wrote her first novels, Diary without Dates (1918) and The Happy Foreigner (1920). Bagnold married Sir Roderick Jones in 1920, settled in London, traveled in high society and literary circles, and for the next three decades continued writing fiction. In 1924, she published Serena Blandish and in 1938 The Squire (published under the title The Door of Life in the United States). After losing her first chance to be on stage, Bagnold turned to playwriting. A friend suggested she use her experience as the plot of a play: "Lottie Dundass" (1941) was the result. She became devoted to the theater and wrote "Poor Judas" (1951), "Gertie" (1952), "The Last Joke" (1960), and "The Chinese Prime Minister" (1964). Her plays were produced in both England and America.
After her husband died in 1962, Bagnold remained active, built new friendships, and continued to write. In 1967 she began her autobiography, which was published in 1969. Although many of her plays were unsuccessful, her enthusiasm for the theater never waned. She flew to Philadelphia in 1977 to attend her play "A Matter of Gravity" starring Katherine Hepburn. Bagnold died in 1981.
Scope and Contents
The Enid Bagnold Papers contain personal and professional correspondence and other papers which document the life and career of the author of National Velvet and "The Chalk Garden." The papers span the years 1912-71.
The Bagnold Papers are divided into two series: Personal Papers and Correspondence. The bulk of the collection consists of letters written to Bagnold, although there are also letters by Bagnold and a small quantity of third party correspondence.
Series I, Personal Papers, is divided into three sections: copies of letters from Bagnold where no other correspondence exists, correspondence with booksellers regarding The Door of Life, and a scrapbook. Bagnold's letters are arranged chronologically, with the notes, drafts, and miscellaneous material following. The Door of Life correspondence consists of chronologically arranged postcards distributed by the William Morrow & Company, publisher, for comments from book vendors, replies to those postcards, and unsolicited reviews. The scrapbook has been photocopied and the original letters placed in the correspondence series. Original material that did not fit in correspondence has been placed in a separate folder.
Series II, General Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, and unidentified correspondence has been placed at the end of the series. Most third person correspondence has been placed in Series I.
Series II does not contain a significant quantity of correspondence from any single individual. There are several groups of ten of more letters, but most individuals wrote just a few letters. The letters are predominantly personal in content, but they also include some discussion of Bagnold's work. The collection contains a handful of business letters.
Almost all the correspondence dating from 1918-19 comments on her first novel Diary without Dates. The production of "Lottie Dundass" is discussed in the Charles Cochran correspondence, while Thornton Wilder's letters critique the play. Probably the best documented work is her play "The Chalk Garden." Letters from Christopher Busney give some hint as to the genesis of the play, while Bagnold's correspondence with Sir James Cassels demonstrates how she acquired legal facts for her plot. Finally some information on the New York and London productions of "The Chalk Garden" can be found in the Irene Selznick and the Brandt & Brandt Dramatic Department correspondence.
Bagnold's correspondence with Arthur Calder-Marshall and William Heineman Limited demonstrates her business manner. There is a rich correspondence with Alfred Lunt and Lynn Fontanne, a friendship that arose when Bagnold offered them the leading roles in "The Chinese Prime Minister." Another interesting correspondent is Hugo Rumbold, who wrote to Bagnold using the name "Marie." Known in the theater world as "Binkie," Hugh Beaumont, corresponded with Bagnold and is often mentioned in other correspondence.
The collection also contains letters from such prominent political and literary figures as Irene Selznick, Stanley Baldwin, William Somerset Maugham, J. B. Priestley, Thornton Wilder, and Katherine Mansfield.
The fragile papers in Box 4 consist of originals for which preservation photocopies have been made.
Autographs; English drama -- 20th Century; Authors; Dramatists; Alfonso, Beatriz; Alfonso, Maria Francisco Antonio Diego; Bagnold, Enid; Bedford, Sybille, 1911-2006; Behrman, S. N. (Samuel Nathaniel), 1893-1973; Calder-Marshall, Arthur, 1908-; Cochran, C. B. (Charles Blake), 1872-1951; Fontanne, Lynn, 1887-1983; Lunt, Alfred, 1892-1977; Morand, Paul, 1888-1976; Selznick, Irene Mayer, 1907-1990; Smyth, Ethel, 1858-1944; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975
- Personal papers, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Personal Papers, Folder 1 contains copies of letters by Bagnold arranged chronologically. Notes and other material follow the letters. The correspondence with booksellers is also arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence and notes, 1962-63 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with booksellers re: The Door of Life:, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook
    - Photocopy of scrapbook
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Oversize, Box 3, folder 63
    - Material from scrapbook, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- General correspondence, Series II
  Series II, General Correspondence, Within the series, letters are arranged alphabetically. For each individual, correspondence is in chronological order, with undated letters at the end.
  - Alfonso, Maria Francisco Antonio Diego and Alfonso, Beatriz, 1925-68 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Arlen, Michael, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Asquith, Emma Alice Margaret, Countess of Oxford and Asquith, 1919, 1942
  - Asquith, Violet, Baroness of Yarnsbury and Bonham Carter, Maurice, Sir, 1918-49 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Asselin, Maurice, 1916, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bagnold, Alexander, ca. 1918
  - Baker, Sylvia, 1934 Jan 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Baldwin, Stanley, 1931
  - Balfour, W. J., 1935 Apr 24
  - Barker, Lee
    See: Doubleday & Co., Box 1, folder 27
  - Beaton, Cecil, 1943, n.d.
  - Beauchamp, Kathleen
    See: Mansfield, Katherine, Box 1 folder 36
  - Beaumont, Hugh, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Beaverbrook, William Maxwell Aitken, 1st Baron, 1962, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bedford, Sibylle, Lady Cunard, 1925-71 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Beer-Hoffmann, Gabriel, 1936 Feb 15 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Behrman, S. N., 1928-67 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bell, Arthur Clive Howard, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bell, Quentin, 1970 Nov 7
  - Bellingham-Smith, Hugh, n.d.
  - Belloc, Hilaire, 1939 Aug 7
  - Beresford, John Davys, 1920 Mar 6
  - Besant, Annie, 1912 Aug 15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Birkenhead, Frederick Edwin Smith, 1st Earl, 1950, n.d.
  - Birrell, Augustine, 1918-32
  - Blackwood, Basil, Sir, 1916
  - Blumenfeld, Ralph D., 1935 Apr 11
  - Bonham-Carter, Maurice, Sir
    See: Asquith, Violet, Baroness of Yarnsbury, Box 1 folder 6
  - Bonham-Carter, Violet
  - Brandt & Brandt Dramatic Dept., 1952-56 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Brandt, Carol
    See: Brandt & Brandt Dramatic Dept., Box 1 folder 16
  - Buckingham, Gwen, Lady, ca. 1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Burroway, Janet, 1971 Nov 23 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Busney, Christopher, 1971
  - Calder-Marshall, Arthur, [1953] (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Camrose, Mollie Patricia, Viscountess, [1956?] Jan 15 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Cassels, James Dale, Sir, 1952
  - Cecil, David, Lord, 1948 Nov 9
  - Chamberlain, Anne, Lady, 1938-39
  - Churchill, Clementine Oglivy Spencer, Baroness, 1945-62
  - The Clarion, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Clark, Dora, 1963
  - Cochran, Charles Blake, 1941-45 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Compton, William Bingham, 6th Marquess of Northampton, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Compton-Burnett, Ivy, 1955 Feb 19
  - Connolly, Cyril Vernon, 1973, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Cooper, Diana, Lady, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cooper, Reginald, 1951
    See also: Oversize, Box 3, folder 64
  - Cowan, S. Hunter, n.d.
  - Cunard, Emerald, Lady, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Cutmore, F. B., ca. 1940
  - Daily Mail, 1918 Jan 28
  - D'erlanger, Catherine, Baroness, n.d. Jul 3
  - Desborough, Ethel, 1918 Mar 4 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Doubleday & Co., 1953 Nov 24
  - Dramatists Guild, 1956 Feb 1
  - [Du Paty de Clam, Champlouis?], 1919 Apr 9
  - [Duff, Juliet, Lady?], ca. 1941 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Dyson, William, n.d.
  - Elliott, Mary, n.d.
  - Evans, Dwye
    See: William Heinemann, Ltd., Box 2 folder 57
  - Fontanne, Lynn
    See: Lunt, Alfred, Box 1 folder 35
  - Freedman, Harold
  - Fry, Christopher, 1970 Feb 20
  - Garvin, James Louis and Garvin, Viola, 1920-33 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Gordon, Ruth, 1952, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Gosse, Edmund William, Sir, 1918 Mar 2
  - Gutherie, William Tyrone, Sir, 1954 Jan 22
  - Hall, Rosalind, 1952 Jan 24
  - Hamilton, Cicely, [pre-1928] Jul 28
  - Harding, Gilbert Charles, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Harris, Jed, n.d.
  - Hartley, Leslie Poles, 1962
  - Hodgson, Ralph, 1956 Sept 3
  - Horobin, Norah M., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Houghton Mifflin Co., 1958 Jul 28
  - Huxley, Julian Sorell, 1969 Jan 22
  - Jeffs, Julian, 1963
  - Jesse, Fryniwyd Tennyson, 1912, n.d.
  - Kelly, Felix, 1961 Jun 7 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Kingsmill, Hugh, 1915-39
  - Knoblock, Edward, n.d.
  - Kouyoumdjian, Dirran
    See: Arlen, Michael
  - Krishnamurti, Jiddu, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Laverly, John, Sir, 1932 Nov 16
  - Lovat, Laura, Lady, 1942 Dec 28
  - Lunn, Hugh
    See: Kingsmill, Hugh, Box 1 folder 32
  - Lunt, Alfred and Fontanne, Lynn, [1962]-73 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Lutyens, Edwin Landseer, Sir, 1928, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - McIndoe, Archibald, Sir, 1956 Dec 15
  - Mais, Stuart Petre Brodie, 1951 Feb 20
  - Manchester Guardian, 1918 Jan 28
  - Mansfield, Katherine, n.d.
  - Marowe, G. S.
    See: Beer-Hoffmann, Gabriel, Box 1 folder 12
  - Marsh, Edward Howard, Sir, 1916 Jun 20 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Mason, Alfred Edward Woodley, 1943 Aug 23
  - Massey, Vincent, 1957 Aug 8
  - Massie, Chris, 1931 Dec 13
  - Massington, Harold John, 1918 Jan 31
  - Massingham, Henry William, n.d. Jun 3 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Maugham, William Somerset, n.d. Aug 29
  - Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer, 1942 Nov 23
  - Meynell, Viola, 1942, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - [Moore, Marcia?], 1962 Nov 14
  - Moorehead, Alan McCrae, 1956 Dec 1
  - Morand, Paul, 1931-1965 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Murray, Rosalind, 1912 Oct 31 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Neale, Randal, 1936, n.d.
  - Nicholson, William Newzman Prior, Sir, 1943
  - Orage, Alfred Richard, n.d.
  - Painter, George Duncan, 1965 Dec 18 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Pearson, Edward Hesketh Gibbons, 1962 May 14
  - Poole, Reginald Ward Edward Lane, Sir, 1935 May 28
  - Priestley, John Boynton, 1952 May 20
  - Quentin, Pol, 1963 Sep 16
  - Ravenshill, H. C., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Richardson, Constance Stewart
    See: Stewart-Richardson, Constance, Box 2 folder 43
  - Rider, Dan, 1918 Mar 2
  - Rothenstein, Albert Daniel
    See: Rutherston, Albert Daniel, Box 2 folder 45
  - Rouse, A. L., [1951?] Jun 9 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Rumbold, Hugo, 1917
  - Rumbold, Richard, 1942, n.d.
  - Rutherston, Albert Daniel, 1914-1919 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Sampson, George, 1918 Mar 13 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Sands, Ethel, 1933, n.d.
  - Sasson, Philip Albert Gustave David, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Seaman, Owen, 1911, 1918
  - Selincourt, Irene de, 1963
  - Selznick, Daniel Mayer, 1955
  - Selznick, David O., 1956
  - Selznick, Irene Mayer, 1956, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Shebel, Victor, n.d.
  - Shepard, Ernest, 1913 Jul 27
  - Shumlin, Herman, 1951, 1952
  - Sichel, Walter, 1918 Jan 27
  - Simon and Schuster, Inc., 1958 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Smith, Logan Pearsall, 1918, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Smyth, Ethel Mary, Dame, 1919-40 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Stein, Toby, 1963, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Stewart-Richardson, Constance, n.d.
  - Sunday Times, 1938 Nov 8
  - Thirkell, Angela Margaret, 1942 May 27
  - Times Literary Supplement, 1951 Sep 11 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Tonks, Henry, 1933 Dec 25
  - Tree, Herbert Beerbohm, Sir, 1913 Oct 17
  - Tritton, Robert, 1956 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Turner, Walter James, 1918 Nov 5
  - Van Druten, John William, 1956 Jan 1
  - [Walker, Leslie J.?], 1935 Nov 5 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Waller, Harold, 1938, 1954
  - Weales, Gerald, 1959 Mar 10
  - Webb, Alan, 1963
  - Wedgwood, Cicely Veronica, 1959 Dec 19 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Whiting, John Robert, 1951 Sep 15
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1941, 1972
  - William Heinemann, Ltd., 1952-53 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - William Morrow & Co., 1957 Jul 18 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Willis, Irene Cooper, 1941, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Woodman-Smith, Cecil Blanche, 1955 May 24
  - Woolf, Leonard Sidney, 1962 Oct 3
  - Worsley, T. Cuthbert, 1962-63 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Young, Filson, 1914 Feb 23 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Young, Frances Brett, 1919 May 8
  - Yule, J. S., Lt. Col., 1955
  - Unidentified Correspondents (Box 2, Folder 62)
- Oversize, n.d.
  - Photocopy of scrapbook, n.d. (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 63)
  - Cooper, Reginald: Musical score, n.d. (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 64)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.25' (1 box)
  Box 4, Restricted Fragile Papers, contains fragile originals and the material is arranged in folder order.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 1, 1962 Jan 6 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 65)
  - Box 1, folder 1, 1911 Jun 2 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 66)
  - Box 1, folder 2, 1938 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 67)
  - Box 1, folder 4, 1952 Mar 22 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 68)
  - Box 1, folder 5, 1942 Sep 1 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 69)
  - Box 1, folder 13, 1929 Jan 2 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 70)
  - Box 1, folder 15, 1950, n.d. (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 71)
  - Box 1, folder 16, 1956 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 72)
  - Box 1, folder 19, [1953], n.d. (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 73)
  - Box 1, folder 20, 1945 Oct 12 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 74)
  - Box 1, folder 22, 1942 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 75)
  - Box 1, folder 41, n.d. (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 76)